{
  "reference_number": "11659",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "It is imperative that we act now and put in place a clear target now so we can act on climate change now"
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "Emissions are what is causing climate change so that is what must be reduced to net zero. I support an overall target of net zero\n across all gases by 2050. We need to reduce all greenhouse gases, including methane."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "I support the most ambitious target of reducing total greenhouse gases to net zero by 2050. I also support taking a science-based\n\n approach to ensure our efforts to reduce emissions are as impactful as possible: we should aim for negative levels of long-lived\n gases, while reducing short-lived gases to sustainable levels. This target should be reached by reducing our own emissions and not\n\n by using international carbon credits."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The 2050 target should only be revised in exceptional circumstances. The purpose of the Zero Carbon Act is to provide\n accountability, certainty and flexibility. It will provide accountability and certainty by setting clear, legally-binding emission reduction\n targets. It will retain flexibility by permitting different governments to use different policies to meet these targets, in response to\n\n changing circumstances and new technology. Despite the importance of accountability and certainty, there are some situations\n where it is appropriate to change the 2050 target. Only in exceptional conditions where the target can become more ambitious\n\n should the government change the target. There should be safeguards to only increase the target to reduce New Zealand's\n emissions further. For example, making the target more ambitious should only be considered if say the Paris Climate Agreement\n becomes more ambitious. I do not support being able to revise the 2050 target in response to “economic changes”. This would\n\n create uncertainty, which means more economic instability, rather than less."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I support this. Legally-binding budgets, set 10-15 years in advance so that 3 budgets are in effect at all times, at a level\n\n recommended by the Climate Commission and approved by Parliament, are essential to the success of the Zero Carbon Act."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "No. Budgets should only be revised in exceptional circumstances. It is not appropriate for a new government to “have a say” on an\nupcoming budget which has already been set. This would create too much uncertainty and instability. What a new government can\n\ndo is introduce different policies to meet the upcoming target. Climate change is not a political football that can be kicked around.\nOur lives, our homes, our land and our children's futures are facing catastrophic disaster and this budget should not be changed\n\ndepending on the government of the day."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Under exceptional circumstances, yes. For example, it might be appropriate to change an upcoming budget after an extreme natural\n\ndisaster (such as a major earthquake). Revising a budget in this situation would not mean changing the long-term 2050 target. To\nprovide maximum certainty and accountability, budgets should not be revised unless the circumstances are exceptional."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I generally agree with the proposed list of considerations to take into account when setting emission budgets: 1. scientific\n\nknowledge about climate change 2. technology relevant to climate change 3. economic circumstances and, in particular, the likely\nimpact of the decision on the economy and the competitiveness of particular sectors of the economy 4. fiscal circumstances and, in\n\nparticular, the likely impact of the decision on taxation, public spending and public borrowing 5. social circumstances and, in\nparticular, the likely impact of the decision on fuel poverty 6. energy policy and, in particular, the likely impact of the decision on\nenergy supplies and the carbon and energy intensity of the economy 7. the government’s obligations under the Treaty of Waitangi 8.\n\nthe three government objectives for climate change policy: sustainable economy, global and local leadership and creating a just and\ninclusive society"
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I support the Zero Carbon Act having a strict time frame for setting out policy plans. This time frame should be 6 months after an\nemission budget has been set."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The Government’s policy plans to meet emission budgets should be comprehensive, fair, cost-effective, environmentally sustainable,\n\nand reflect a commitment to Te Tiriti o Waitangi. Zero Carbon Act principles are explained as: Fairness means giving effect to equity\nconsiderations, such as intergenerational justice and the principles of a “just transition”. In practice, this means ensuring that\n\nvulnerable communities are supported, that there is a just transition for workers in industries where job losses will occur, and that\nclear signals are given as early as possible to enable communities and businesses to plan for the impact and opportunities of\n\nemission reduction policies (as well as the effects of climate change, such as sea level rise). Cost-effectiveness means adopting\nlong-term strategies which minimise cost and maximise benefits for New Zealand. In particular, this means setting targets and plans\nthat avoid passing the cost of transition to young and future generations. Comprehensiveness means taking an economy-wide\n\napproach to New Zealand’s emission reduction strategy. The strategy must encompass all sectors, drive coordinated decision-\nmaking and analysis across government, and be sufficiently funded and resourced. Environmental sustainability means considering\n\nthe holistic environmental impact of climate change policies, not only the extent of greenhouse gas reductions."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes. I support the Climate Commission having two functions: (a) providing expert advice, and (b) monitoring our progress and holding\nthe government to account. The Commission should not be a decision-making body, for the following reasons: Democratic\n\naccountability: Elected officials should be ultimately responsible for making plans and meeting Zero Carbon Act targets. If they mess\nup, we vote them out. The Commission, in contrast, is not democratically elected or accountable to the public. Similarly, the\ngovernment should not be able to ‘pass the buck’ on difficult decisions to the Commission. The Commission should provide expert\n\nadvice, but it is the government that must take responsibility. Compromised watchdog: A Commission with decision-making powers\nwill be a less effective watchdog. It would have a conflict of interest in holding itself to account over its own policy decisions.\n\nComprehensive policy plans: Transitioning to a zero carbon economy will require comprehensive and coordinated policies across all\nsectors of the economy. The government needs to assume overall responsibility for these plans. Delegating some decision-making\n\npowers to the Commission (such as ETS settings, see Q12) risks these policies being made without properly coordinating with\npolicies elsewhere."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "The Climate Commission should only advise on ETS settings, it should not make final decisions."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I generally agree with the proposed list of expertise which should be collectively held by the Climate Commission: climate change\npolicy (including emissions trading) resource economics and impacts (including social impacts, labour markets and distribution) te\n\nTiriti o Waitangi, te reo me ona tikanga Māori and Māori interests climate and environmental science including mātauranga Māori\nexperience with addressing adaptation challenges like planning, insurance and local government risk management engineering\n\nand/or infrastructure community engagement and communications. Desirable, but non-essential, expertise could include: business\ncompetitiveness knowledge of the public and private innovation and technology development system."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes. I support the inclusion of adaptation (this means addressing the impacts of climate change, such as droughts and sea level rise)\nin the Zero Carbon Act. The Climate Commission should contribute its expertise to our adaptation response."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes. I support the government being required to prepare a national climate risk assessment, and a national policy plan to address\nthese risks. A monitoring and reporting framework is also important. We need to think carefully about how local councils should be\n\ninvolved in these processes."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes. I support exploring this option in more detail."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I want to live in an Aotearoa that acts on Climate Change and protects the country and the people that I love. Generation Zero has\n\nbeen a leading organisation in acting on climate change and should be consulted with on an ongoing basis regarding these matters.\nThis bill should always adhere to the following principles: Fairness means giving effect to equity considerations, such as\n\nintergenerational justice and the principles of a “just transition”. In practice, this means ensuring that vulnerable communities are\nsupported, that there is a just transition for workers in industries where job losses will occur, and that clear signals are given as early\n\nas possible to enable communities and businesses to plan for the impact and opportunities of emission reduction policies (as well as\nthe effects of climate change, such as sea level rise). Cost-effectiveness means adopting long-term strategies which minimise cost\nand maximise benefits for New Zealand. In particular, this means setting targets and plans that avoid passing the cost of transition to\n\nyoung and future generations. Comprehensiveness means taking an economy-wide approach to New Zealand’s emission reduction\nstrategy. The strategy must encompass all sectors, drive coordinated decision-making and analysis across government, and be\n\nsufficiently funded and resourced. Environmental sustainability means considering the holistic environmental impact of climate\nchange policies, not only the extent of greenhouse gas reductions.\n\n\n\n\n You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
